<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>newsletter</title>
<link>https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/</link>
<atom:link href="https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>ADCN - Athletes Data Community Newsletter</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.24</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>ADCN: Health Algorithms &amp; Interfaces, Data Duty of Care, Injury Reports</title>
  <dc:creator>Brad Stenger</dc:creator>
  <link>https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/posts/ADCN_5/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The ADCN newsletter archive can be found at <a href="https://newsletter.bradstenger.com" class="uri">https://newsletter.bradstenger.com</a>. I mention it here for two reasons. First, the site construction needs some attention and some work, and this public announcement will make it more likely to see those improvements occur sooner rather than later. Second, the website has a sign up where anyone can give their email to join ADCN’s mailing list. I’m still soft-launching ADCN but the public launch is coming. Getting the ADCN web presence up and running is a crucial step.</p>
<section id="health-algorithms-and-the-lowest-common-denominator" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="health-algorithms-and-the-lowest-common-denominator">Health Algorithms and the Lowest Common Denominator</h3>
<p>Personalization algorithms, in general, do not work so well when those algorithms have to serve thousands (or millions) of users. The situation is a classic case where usability has to function at a lowest common denominator across a population where the variation is substantial.</p>
<p>For some people, especially people who trust machine instructions with little or no question, and in terms of demographics this population skews young, there is also an inabilitiy to contextualize recommendations that come from an AI source. Failing to understand AI in context makes human error likely despite confidence that is out of proportion with reality, mostly because reality gets ignored.</p>
<p>Every once in a while the scientific literature presents a window into health data recommendation systems and its lowest common denominator. Apple <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0334950">recently published</a> in <em>PLOS One</em> results from the company’s sleep tracking study that took data from more than 35,000 Apple watch wearers who use the device as a sleep tracker. Most sleep data collection occurs in 1-14 day windows, predominantly at the low end, and it under-estimates the night to night sleep variability across populations. Apple simulated longer duration datasets and subsampled that data in an attempt to understand the depth of the problem with short-duration sleep samples.</p>
<p>Apple researchers stratified groups into one-hour intervals, and came to realize that the smaller group of lighter sleepers (6 +/- 1 hours) could not be differentiated from the more common heavier (7 +/- 1 hours) sleepers. “For the planning of future [sleep measurement] studies, there may be a resource and/or participant burden tension between sample size and duration of tracking,” the author conclude, saying “the path to mitigation lies in duration of tracking per participant, more so than boosting cohort sample size.”</p>
<p>Sleep is incredibly complex. <a href="https://x.com/SatchinPanda/status/1982819322868498688">Recent mouse studies</a> suggest close links between seasonal variation in diet and circadian rhythm. Circadian rhythm may need to be measured for long (probably very long) duration in order to understand seasonal, annual, reproductive, and human life stage variations in sleep, and in turn, recovery and performance. These are evolutionary forces at work where subtle and deep-seated adaptions have major, meaningful implications. Human physiological and cognitive adaptions for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Born_to_Run_(McDougall_book)">running</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cooked:_A_Natural_History_of_Transformation">cooking</a> helped to shape human existence over long term time frames. Is socialized, high exertion, inter-personal competition, also known as sports, fundamentally human and a generator of physiological and cognitive adaption? I wouldn’t rule it out.</p>
<p>So what is AI good for when it comes to health and performance data? Arjun Mahajan and Stephen Gilbert gave their opinion in a <em>Nature Digital Medicine</em> <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-025-02093-0">essay</a>, “Do we need AI guardians to protect us from health information overload?” Guardians are necessary, they write, because commercial health data devices send too many low-value alerts that miss what a health assistant should target, which are “filtering, contextualizing, and personalizing health information” for users.</p>
<p>Threshold values in biometric data are a consistently useful interaction that the authors mention, and they do best when the data user specifies the target threshold (like heart rate during zone training). User-specified targets are personalized, contextualized, and filtered, all because a human sets all of those parameters when they go about creating the target alert on their device. Keeping a human in the feedback seems far more useful than a completely automated AI when it comes to data-backed health and performance information.</p>
<p>Sports have coaches. If path to personalization benefits from human input then there should be a place for coaches’ input on behalf of athletes, especially when it comes to determining useful athletes’ thresholds. Putting a coach (or coaches) in the feedback loop should help to avoid low-value alerts and to keep things personal, contextual and filtered. Problems will arise when misaligned incentives prompt coaches to not prioritize athletes’ best interests. In general athletes trust coaches. Give coaches the benefit of the doubt and to make their input for athlete threshold settings a default (or a low-effort optional setting), at least to start.</p>
<p>How things start might not be how things end up. There are signs that AI recommendation systems can and will be gamed by a servcice’s self-interests, and not in users’ best interests. <a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2025/11/ai-summarization-optimization.html">A post</a> at Bruce Schneier’s blog describes the phenomena of AI Summary Optimization. The situation is analogous to Search Engine Optimization from 10-15 years ago. AISO is the new SEO. Keywords and content sequences, often jargon, factor into the subjective assessment made by an AI recommender system. Start down the path from automated threshold notification to subjective recommendations and from there it is a slippery slope to low-value alerts.</p>
</section>
<section id="duty-of-care-for-data" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="duty-of-care-for-data">Duty of Care for Data</h3>
<p>The FAIR consensus reports are <a href="https://bjsm.bmj.com/search/FAIR%252Bconsensus%20jcode%3Abjsports">a series of review papers</a> that examine “prevention strategies and modifiable risk factors” for female, woman and girl athletes. The papers have been appearing regularly in the <em>British Journal of Sports Medicine</em> and cover their review process and the targets for injury prevention such as concussion, upper extremities, lower extremities, etc. The series recently concluded with articles and essays that discuss dissemination and implementation of FAIR findings and recommendations. The challenge of translating medicine and transferring technology from research to practice is difficult on its easiest day. Any how-to guide will still have difficulty leading interested stakeholders to successful outcomes. Competence and its polar opposite, negligence, are difficult to identify during research translation, and without identifiable best and worst practices, the road map to a better place (or away from a worse place) is not clear or obvious.</p>
<p>If there is one guiding principal for athletes’ health it is the idea of <a href="https://assets.publishing.service.gov.uk/media/5a81ff3c40f0b62305b91ed9/Duty_of_Care_Review_-_April_2017__2.pdf">duty of care</a>. Duty of care is a legal standard and a social norm and, in general, reflects an individual’s responsibility for the well-being of others. Duty of care means that coaches do not overwork players, that one player does not cheap shot another player, that equipment is safe, that medical staff are available, and any other measure to prevent forseeable harm. Duty of care is also a legal standard, and when breached can result in judgements of negligence and liability.</p>
<p>Duty of care does not as yet extend to athletes’ data and information, either in its legal or social context. But maybe it should. Duty of care already exists in the context of injury prevention. Greater awareness of its potential application to athletes’ data and information would incentivize action to translate research into practice.</p>
<p>Another recent BJSM review paper is <a href="https://blogs.bmj.com/bjsm/2025/11/03/can-the-menstrual-cycle-phase-impact-sports-performance/">an audit</a> of the effect female menstrual cycles have on sports injuries of all types and among all genders. (This was not a FAIR consensus review.) Injury analysis papers, the authors found, look primarily at evidence from male athletes and when they do consider female athletes’ evidence it does not account for hormonal fluctuations, despite the significant bearing that menstrual cycles have on injury occurrence. There’s a case to make that any aggregate injury analysis needs to account for cycles and their role. There’s also a case to make that cycles have enormous variation and it will take great effort to understand and account for the role of menstrual cycles in sports injury. Duty of care would suggest that there is an essential need to understand injury occurrences and prevention. If some analysis that takes shortcuts can help, those studies are valuable. But there is also an obligation to do the difficult, time-consuming work to understand the full scope of athlete injuries.</p>
<p>Concussions, among all athletes, have long been a duty of care quagmire. Recall how long it took for American football to recognize <a href="https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/sports/league-of-denial/timeline-the-nfls-concussion-crisis/">its problem with concussions</a>. Looking the other way was far easier than solving the difficult problem of football concussions when solutions meant changing fundamentals of the game, but eventually duty of care was applied and change happened. Concussion diagnosis still does not have objective criteria and relies on athletes’ self-reporting (often reluctant). Canada’s Sport Information Resource Centre took <a href="https://sirc.ca/articles/sharing-responsibility-for-concussion-symptom-reporting-and-removal-from-play-in-youth-sport-it-takes-a-village/">the stance</a> that concussion symptoms reporting is a shared “duty of care” responsibility that cuts across all sports’ participants and at every level. Sports participation should not exist within a broader sports culture “that tolerates (and sometimes celebrates) pain and injury, and privileges performance over health,” the authors write. The authors are sport injury researchers at Canadian universities and they emphasize awareness and communication in their “it takes a village” solution.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.mhsaa.com/topics/coaches/staying-ahead-head-safety">A recent meeting</a> among Michigan high school sports administrators pointed to the considerable costs, inconsistent practices, and high stakes, the greatest of which are to athletes who are false-positives and pass their on-field cognitive evalutation. The need is for fast, accurate concussion exams in a Canada-like framework that prioritizes long-term health and well-being.</p>
<p>The legal dimension to duty of care makes it intimidating to cite duty of care in any context where there is risk of litigation. Personal injury law can be seen working at the periphery of sports to call out negligence and liability. The more important context is athletes’ health and well-being however, and duty of care should motivate the advances in sports management and coaching practice that research and technology make possible.</p>
</section>
<section id="injury-reports" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="injury-reports">Injury Reports</h3>
<p>Haralabob Voulgaris made tens of millions of dollars as a professional gambler on sports. Speaking with Pablo Torre on <a href="https://www.pablo.show/p/the-nbas-winningest-gambler-has-a">a podcast</a> Voulgaris said that the NBA has a real integrity problem when it came to the team injury reports, especially with regard to the relationship between those reports and gambling. Voulgaris did not cite any specific example of improper or illegal activity but did describe how different teams approach the injury reports differently, with varying levels of effort and accuracy. Injury report information is crucial to serious sports gamblers who are anxious to know anything that could favor (or disfavor) their action. The team-by-team differences in report production and quality make it difficult to police public information which make it possible for insider information to leak (or spill) out in sports gambling contexts.</p>
<p>The news about injury reports is not really about the NBA though. The NCAA <a href="https://sbcamericas.com/2025/10/31/ncaa-player-injury-report-march-madness/">now requires</a> player availability reports for the 2026 men’s and women’s Division 1 basketball tournaments. Public injury reports have been required for football in the SEC, Big Ten, ACC and Mid-American conferences. The SEC and ACC also require reports for men’s and women’s basketball, and for baseball. The NCAA pointed out that the reports keep gambling interests from interacting directly with student-athletes about their health status.</p>
<p>A medical school student and two professors wrote <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2025/09/21/nfl-injury-list-sports-betting-athlete-medical-privacy/">an opinion essay</a> in the medical news outlet <em>STAT</em>, saying that the personal information contained in team injury reports would constitute a serious privacy violation if they had not been subject to collective bargaining and contractual language between the athletes and their leagues. The origin of injury reports dates to 1947 when the NFL commission learned of dramatic shifts in betting leading up to a game where a flu had significantly compromised one team. The authors, two Yale doctors and a Case Western lawyer, say that it’s enough to say that an athlete will not compete, and any potentially invasive details are not necessary. As NCAA athletes become more subject to injury reporting requirements there is no indication who or how anyone will defend their privacy interests in the disclosures.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/posts/ADCN_5/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
