<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>newsletter</title>
<link>https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/</link>
<atom:link href="https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>ADCN - Athletes Data Community Newsletter</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.24</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>ADCN: Open Biomechanics Research, U.S. Sport Policy, News</title>
  <dc:creator>Brad Stenger</dc:creator>
  <link>https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/posts/ADCN_9/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="university-research-in-open-biomechics" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="university-research-in-open-biomechics">University Research in Open Biomechics</h3>
<p>The KneeHub project just published <a href="https://asmedigitalcollection.asme.org/biomechanical/article/doi/10.1115/1.4070823/1229924/Deciphering-the-Art-in-Modeling-and-Simulation-of">an update</a> to a biomechanics models benchmarking <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC8086182/">study</a> first published in 2021. KneeHub was conceived as a way to determine what’s art and what’s science in the process of constructing biomechanical models. Five teams independently developed knee biomechanics models using their preferred workflow. Different workflows produced different predictions for the same scenarios. But all of the differences could be explained. “Our most important conclusion,” the authors wrote, is “the ability of [biomechanics] models to predict beyond the conditions used to calibrate them.”</p>
<p>The result offers useful validation for personalized approaches to neuromuscular rehabilitation. Another recent advance comes from B.J. Fregly’s group at Rice University. The Neuromusculoskeletal Modeling (NMSM) Pipeline <a href="https://news.rice.edu/news/2025/rice-researchers-engineer-personalized-treatments-movement-impairments">software</a> “allows researchers to work in collaboration with clinicians to construct personalized neuromusculoskeletal computer models of individual patients (i.e., digital twins)” then use those models for surgical or neuromuscular rehabilitation treatments. The digital twin gives clinicians the opportunity to explore and test treatment paths, leading to greater confidence in expected outcomes.</p>
<p>Researchers at the University of California-San Diego combine biomechanical models of athletic training movements with an AI that informs physiological and biomuscular limitation to create models (and videos) that can differentiate risk in athletes’ training movements. <a href="https://today.ucsd.edu/story/generative-ai-can-help-athletes-avoid-injuries">The work</a> is early-stage and the research team plans to add to the number of training movements and incorporate personalization.</p>
<p>This is, I think, what you want to see for progress in Open computational biomechanics. The innovations are not just data, or software, or process. University researchers are pushing in all of those directions at the same time with their projects.</p>
</section>
<section id="u.s.-sport-policy-coming-through-congress-or-not" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="u.s.-sport-policy-coming-through-congress-or-not">U.S. Sport Policy Coming Through Congress (Or Not)</h3>
<p><a href="https://x.com/MarkTMcDevitt/status/2011855029930508684"><img src="https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/posts/ADCN_9/trahan_summit.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>The last two weeks had more mentions of college athlete rights than the last two years. It’s a low bar. There weren’t many.</p>
<p>The change in public sports vocabulary comes, in large part, from new federal legislation timed to coincide with the annual NCAA Convention held in Washington DC and the College Football Playoff Title game between Miami and Indiana (not in Washington DC). The noise in government circles was captured by The Hill’s Dominick Mastrangelo <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/senate/5693051-lawmakers-target-ncaa-profits/">who wrote</a>, “Lawmakers in both parties are outraged at the NCAA and signaling intervention from Congress on athlete compensation and revenue sharing is inevitable.”</p>
<p>More of the cacophony around college sports legislation suggests the opposite, that Congressional intervention in U.S. college sports is a work in progress. Nothing here is actually inevitable, or even seems close to resolution. Distrust for the NCAA is high, making the anti-trust excemption that is central to initial legislation difficult to justify, especially since anti-trust and court judgements are the main recourse for college student-athletes who lack for the rights that employees have (just for being employees).</p>
<p>Sports law reporter Michael McCann <a href="https://www.sportico.com/law/analysis/2025/score-act-punt-congress-courts-judges-1234878524/">calls</a> federal legislation “doomed from the start.” Law scholars Sam Ehrlich and Ryan Rodenberg <a href="https://cardozolawreview.com/the-score-act-is-unconstitutional-private-nondelegation-problems-with-congresss-latest-attempt-to-regulate-college-sports/">write</a> that the oversight granted to the NCAA with an anti-trust excemptioon is probably unconstitutional.</p>
<p>Uncertainty around the NCAA has created an enforcement void. <a href="https://sports.yahoo.com/college-football/article/we-are-money-laundering--with-schools-bending-or-breaking-new-rules-sec-and-others-mull-new-governance-model-215315905.html">Reporting</a> by Ross Dellenger noted that the House settlement has not been effective rule-making due to nonexistant penalties. Conferences are ready to step in, University of Georgia president Jere Morehead, a former chair of the NCAA DI Board of Directors, told Dellenger. “We’d be able to make a much stronger argument that we are not in violation of antitrust rules because we don’t have market power.”</p>
<p>An example of enforcement on a a smaller conference-level scale is the 2023 Jim Harbaugh suspension for sign-stealing during a football championship season which preceded NCAA penalties. Rodenberg, in <a href="https://journals.indianapolis.iu.edu/index.php/jlas/article/view/28474/26142">another legal journal article</a>, writes that conferences have an anti-competitive blank check if they’re willing to use it, citing how the Ivy League unilaterly refused scholarships to athletes.</p>
<p>The timing for all of this discussion around college football’s biggest game is no coincidence. The dollars coming to college football winners (schools, conferences, the NCAA and broadcasters) are <a href="https://thenationaldesk.com/news/americas-news-now/the-big-money-behind-college-footballs-storybook-national-championship-football-sports-ncaa-miami-indiana-hoosiers-hurricanes">substantial</a>. The major federal legislation to intervene in college sports has been <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k7oApsxLs_M">consistent with a money grab</a>. Student-athlete interests, outside of the small number of big-money sports (football, basketball), factor little into the college sports money grab.</p>
<p>Except, maybe not. Athlete rights figured prominently in the discussion at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-uKf9UdL-sI">the Congressional College Athletics Summit</a> organized by Massachusetts Representative Lori Trahan. Trahan, a former college volleyball player, sponsored <a href="https://www.sportsbusinessjournal.com/Articles/2025/12/01/trahan-to-introduce-new-college-sports-bill-with-federal-nil-policy-media-rights-amendments/">the latest example</a> of college sports intervention legislation, the College Athletics Reform Act. At the Summit, anti-trust attorney Julia Duncan <a href="https://x.com/WinterSportsLaw/status/2011864865296826495">made the point</a> that college athletes have no seat at the bargaining table, something that will not change much if the NCAA and its member schools gain an anti-trust excemption.</p>
<p>These are the early days of sport policy in the U.S., which is to say the public policy around sport. Australia is a country that has had government sport policy for 50 years, going back to the nation’s dismal performance in the Montreal Olympics, according to <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/sports-and-active-living/articles/10.3389/fspor.2025.1656342/full">a research paper</a> by University of Canberra professor Charles Mountifield.</p>
<p>Mountifield makes the point that where sport policy had been national sports participation initiative, it has lately become a professional athlete and sports media policy. Also of late, Australia is <a href="https://www.heartfoundation.org.au/blueprint">a mostly sedentary nation</a>, like the U.S.</p>
<p>The emerging U.S. sport policy looks like a mistake that underrepresents most, nearly all, college student-athletes, and instead represents university commercial interests to those athletes’ detriment.</p>
<p>Awhile back I had a conversation with an analyst who worked for the Chicago Cubs. The injury crisis for baseball pitchers was something he worked on directly, overseeing data sharing between the Cubs, the Tampa Bay Rays and a handful of other MLB teams. Those teams hoped that their data collaboration would help the teams’ researchers to solve, or at least improve, the pitching injuries situation. He also told me about a proposal he had made to MLB to fund biomechanics pitching labs for any NCAA school that would be willing to share its biomechanics and injury-related data. (The idea went nowhere.) If one agrees that data sharing is crucial for reducing sports injuries, then U.S. sport policy can reasonably be understood as, at least in part, public health policy.</p>
<p>A Cubs-like subsidy (sourced to pro sports leagues or to government outlays) could realistically be extended beyond schools with baseball pitchers to any college athlete willing to share their injury-related data, which would be all of their health and performance data. The arrangement would necessitate applied privacy technology (like I work on) to preserve some (though not all) athlete anonymity. At the end of the day the most elite, most valuable athletes would have the most valuable data.</p>
<p>Athletes could be paid according to their exceptionalism within a framework that works for quarterbacks and for water polo players, for SEC athletes and HBCU athletes and Division III athletes, for men and for women. Any organization seeking financial gain from sport policy related to college student-athletes should expect to offset their benefit in ways that support public health efforts around athletes and injuries.</p>
</section>
<section id="news" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="news">News</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://wildcatbluenation.com/will-stein-plan-to-fix-kentucky-football-biggest-roster-red-flag">Will Stein has a plan to fix Kentucky’s biggest roster red flag</a> from <em>Wildcat Blue Nation blog</em> by Drew Holbrook on January 19</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.hudl.com/blog/mauro-mandorino-behind-the-science">It’s Time to Drop Total Running as a KPI in Football</a> from <em>Hudl blog</em> by Mauro Mandorino on January 15</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://x.com/chadcookpt/status/2011071099782476025">A new CEMMT blog with Damian Keter summarizes our mega-mechanisms paper sponsored by ForceNET and published in PLOS One.</a> from <em>X/Twitter</em> by Chad Cook on January 13</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://x.com/INFORMS/status/2013688940901835008">Is it fair that a reliever gets the win after one inning while a starter throws seven scoreless and gets nothing? This OR/MS Today article proposes a better way to assign credit and fix MLB’s flawed win–loss system</a> from <em>X/Twitter</em> by INFORMS on January 20</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2026/01/22/under-armour-says-its-aware-of-data-breach-claims-after-72m-customer-records-were-posted-online/">Under Armour says it’s ‘aware’ of data breach claims after 72M customer records were posted online</a> from <em>TechCrunch</em> by Zack Whittaker on January 22</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/posts/ADCN_9/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
