<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>newsletter</title>
<link>https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/</link>
<atom:link href="https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>ADCN - Athletes Data Community Newsletter</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.24</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>ADCN: Baseball Player Development, Soccer Data Sharing, News</title>
  <dc:creator>Brad Stenger</dc:creator>
  <link>https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/posts/ADCN_11/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Please help me to grow this newsletter and forward it to anyone you think might be interested. Anyone can sign up for the mailing list via the form at <a href="https://newsletter.bradstenger.com">newsletter.bradstenger.com</a>. Thanks!</p>
<section id="athlete-development-baseball-and-every-other-sport" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="athlete-development-baseball-and-every-other-sport">Athlete Development: Baseball and Every Other Sport</h3>
<p>Prospects alert! It’s almost time to begin playing professional baseball. <a href="https://www.espn.com/mlb/story/_/id/47754884/mlb-2026-driveline-baseball-hitting-lab-analytics-edgar-quero-chicago-white-sox">Advances</a> in baseball player development have made college and pro baseball compelling in a way that’s far different from five or ten years ago. The Moneyball foundation of homeruns and strikeouts still defines the modern baseball product and is still monotonous. The <a href="https://undertheknife.substack.com/p/utk-special-12226">good pitchers keep getting injured</a>, which is a problem. But new faces and the dramatic improvement in player skill and performance are eye-opening. It’s an innovation story and who doesn’t like an innovation story.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SNm9c430hR4&amp;t=1265s"><img src="https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/posts/ADCN_11/wfpds.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></a></p>
<figcaption>Josh Hejka answers a question at the Wake Forest baseball seminar in December, 2025.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Josh Hejka made the point during a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SNm9c430hR4&amp;t=1265s">panel at the 2025 Wake Forest Player Development Seminar</a> that the majority of MLB baseball players have reached that level on talent alone. Their development trajectory is just beginning and some percentage will flourish with access to elite biomechanics training programs. So this might be the best part of the season, when you get to see <a href="https://www.espn.com/mlb/story/_/id/47684236/top-100-mlb-prospects-2026-bold-predictions-kevin-mcgonigle-konnor-griffin-jj-wetherholt">bold! predictions</a> on this year’s new faces in MLB. You can read Eno Sarris’ <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/athletic/7010771/2026/02/03/mlb-starting-pitcher-rankings-2026-fantasy-baseball/">giant report</a> on Stuff+ pitcher rankings (which also includes a functional health and sustainability assessment, meant for fantasy baseball but super-interesting nonetheless).</p>
<p>The innovation story around athlete development is big in baseball, but it hits every sport. You can see it in football and quarterback development is central to this year’s Super Bowl. The path to the big game has been different for the Patriots’ Drake Maye and the Seahawks’ Sam Darnold. <a href="https://theringer.com/2026/02/05/nfl/drake-maye-sam-darnold-super-bowl-quarterback-progressions">This article</a> in <em>The Ringer</em> describes how each teams’ offensive coordinator helped their quarterback’s decision-making. There are two ways for a quarterback to read the situation during a passing play.</p>
<p>A quarterback can pre-process the situation if he knows the limitations of the defensive alignment. But football teams have gotten better at disguising defenses and an alternative method for quarterbacking emerged. The quarterback should instead progress from one option, Plan A, to the next, Plan B, and so on. A progression is an easier cognitive problem for a quarterback and with good play design produces winning results. It’s still possible though for smart operators at quarterback and at game planning to get their desired results through preprocessing. The Seahawks are the progression team. The Patriots are the preprocessing team. One team will win Super Bowl LX.</p>
<p>I plan to tell more innovation and player development stories for <a href="https://www.si.com/nba/celtics/onsi/boston-celtics-get-another-critical-performance-from-two-way-player-showing-elite-player-development-system-01kgqatn5mp7">basketball</a>, <a href="https://thehockeynews.com/news/money-and-power/q-a-with-leafs-hayley-wickenheiser-player-development-hockey-s-fishbowl-and-wickfest">hockey</a> and <a href="https://x.com/socceramerica/status/2019878773039014290">soccer</a>, and for <a href="https://www.bradleyscout.com/sports/its-going-to-be-an-exciting-brand-of-baseball-bradley-baseball-prepares-for-first-season-of-dedman-era/">college sports</a> in the ADCN. This is, in many ways, the demand side for athletes’ health and performance data. The supply side is not just the athletes. It’s the technologies to collect and manages the data that inform athlete development. Some of my research into privacy and athletes’ data is precautionary. If I do it well, some of my the work will head off problems that might otherwise slow down the innovation around athlete development. I will be telling those stories in the ADCN too.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-sharing-in-sports-some-of-the-how-and-why" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-sharing-in-sports-some-of-the-how-and-why">Data Sharing in Sports: Some of the How and Why</h3>
<p>The soccer data site <a href="https://fbref.com/en/">FBref</a> no longer has access to the a rich data pipeline provided to it by Opta and StatsPerform. Up until that point FBref was considered to be the most comprehensive no-cost public football data resource. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/athletic/7002196/2026/01/28/fbref-opta-football-data-soccer-analytics/">The loss</a> creates a void in the soccer analytics community and <a href="https://www.theixsports.com/the-ix-soccer/fbrefs-loss-advanced-stats-womens-soccer-data-accessibility/">a major drop</a> in the data resources for global women’s soccer.</p>
<p>This comes at a time when the NFL’s <a href="https://operations.nfl.com/gameday/analytics/big-data-bowl/">2026 Big Data Bowl</a> nears its conclusion. Michael Lopez, the Senior Director of Football Data and Analytics, <a href="">told the Wharton Moneyball podcast</a> that data is a football Field of Dreams, “if you have the data and make it available, they will analyze it.” Data availability is an opportunity for innovation and for community. According to Lopez, the competition and the data availability has strong support from the league and its member teams. The Big Data Bowl also benefits from a complimentary data set that is robust and no cost at <a href="https://nflfastr.com/">nflfastr</a> (accessible using R and Python).</p>
<p>Major League Baseball has its <a href="https://baseballsavant.mlb.com/statcast_search">Statcast pitch-by-pitch data service</a>. This incredible resource (made it possible)[https://news.clemson.edu/bioengineering-ph-d-student-uses-baseball-tech-to-prevent-pitching-injuries-and-grow-analytics-group/] for Connor Moore to use machine learning and biomechanics to reverse engineer pitcher health from the velocity, location and pitch type of their throws. The work earned Moore <a href="https://open.clemson.edu/all_dissertations/4169/">his PhD</a> at Clemson University.</p>
<p>I used to manage <a href="https://developer.nytimes.com/">the APIs at The New York Times</a> and we had strong support for making the data free and accessible. These were tools that the company’s developers could use to help create new products. More important was the participation that the free API generated in the college student hackathon community. The cost was small compared to the benefit. The same appears to be true for the NFL.</p>
<p>Opta and Stats Perform have data services as their main business. (I interned at Stats during grad school.) A data business may not have the public mission of a prestigous news organization or a sports league, and probably needs to enlist a benefactor in order to provide data services that will enable free distribution. There is a decent chance that at some point FIFA or another global soccer operator will restore some kind free data access.</p>
<p>Or it won’t. There does not appear to be any public component to NBA player tracking or biomechanics data. NHL shot and lineup data is available at <a href="https://moneypuck.com/data.htm">MoneyPuck</a> but the advanced player tracking data the the NHL uses for its <a href="https://www.nhl.com/news/nhl-edge-site-new-look-has-advanced-statistics-for-everybody">Edge stats and information site</a>. Corey Sznajder maintains a hockey microstats data service at <a href="https://www.allthreezones.com/">allthreezones.com</a>, something that invites comparison to Baseball Savant and Statcast, which started as a personal data project before MLB took it over.</p>
<p>Sharing data and making money, business makes it so the two go together, but sometimes it’s not an easy fit. Innovations in technology, in computing, in human performance create opportunities for new business models. New ways to do both, share data and make money, will surface as athletes’ data supply and demand continue to evolve. No doubt it is a big help for innovators and entrepreneurs to have access to quality sports data resources at no cost.</p>
</section>
<section id="news" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="news">News</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/02/05/magazine/jessie-diggins-ski-winter-olympics-milan.html">‘All It Is Is Pain’: The Olympian Testing the Limits of Endurance</a> in <em>The New York Times Magazine</em> by Reid Forgrave on February 5, 2026</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/russpoldrack.org/post/3mdxqirfre22v">Metadata, data documentation, and provenance … the latest in my Better Code, Better Science series.</a> in <em>Bluesky</em> by Russ Poldrack on February 3, 2026</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/levakabas.bsky.social/post/3mdvxv2724k23">Michigan just reported a record $67.6 million in football ticket sales for 2024-25</a> in <em>Bluesky</em> by Lev Akabas on February 2, 2026</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://jipel.law.nyu.edu/the-future-of-biometrics-in-formula-1-racing/">The Future of Biometrics in Formula 1 Racing</a> in <em>NYU Journal of Intellectual Property &amp; Entertainment Law</em> by Eleanor Schifino on January 27, 2026</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/athletic/7021527/2026/02/05/real-madrid-masks-training-pintus/">Why are Real Madrid players wearing masks in training?</a> in <em>The Athletic</em> by Mario Cortegna on February 5, 2026</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.npr.org/2026/02/05/nx-s1-5701399/how-college-sports-juiced-olympic-development">How college sports juiced Olympic development</a> in <em>NPR, Planet Money</em> by Wailin Wong, Adrian Ma, Corey Bridges, Kate Concannon on February 5, 2026</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://newsletter.bradstenger.com/posts/ADCN_11/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
